You guys came earlier than I expected.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Thanks for that. Nice
to see you do the Japanese thing here.
Oh, you're going to do the Oh, you want
me to get my And then you have to bow
three times.
And hello world. Today we're spending
time with the Japanese politician that
looks like former US President Bill
Clinton. I know you're all clicking on
this video because he's a white guy. And
John Heath, he's he's okay with that.
He's even played Clinton in movies. And
to answer that burning question people
may have, yes, he is Japanese. He was
born and raised in Canada, but
naturalized and became Japanese back in
2007. So, how in the world did he end up
as a Japanese politician? I really like
traveling and I wanted to go somewhere
to teach English. So, after graduating,
I looked at a bunch of different
countries and decided on Japan. and I
came here on a five-year plan and 33
years later I'm still here. I taught
English and after six years I realized
that I wasn't learning Japanese because
I was speaking English all day. And so I
thought well what can I do? The foreign
bars were becoming a thing like in Tokyo
for example and it's like we have a lot
of foreigners in scuba. So I thought
yeah I'll open up a bar and I did that
for 7 years. In 2002 they changed the
law about drunk driving. When I when I
opened up my bar in 97 was the first
one, if you didn't have a parking lot,
you didn't have a bar. Everybody drove
drunk. It was just the way things were.
And so I started going around to other
establishments and talking to the owners
and just saying, "Hey, like uh this
happened in Canada 20 years ago." What
John's talking about is the Canadian
Club designated driver program. The
Canadian government wanted one person in
a group to be a non-drinker called a
designated driver. As such, they would
get a badge and often free soft drinks.
This was the solution to try and make
sure people didn't drive home drunk
while also keeping businesses running.
These days, there's Uber or Lift, but at
the time it was quite forwardthinking.
From the day they implemented this drunk
driving ban to one year later lost 70%
of sales. Show me a business that can
survive a 70% drop in sales. I remember
complaining a lot. By then all my my
drinking buddies was like, "Oh," rolling
their eyes every time I started getting
on about how police were. And eventually
I said, "Yeah, you know, if I had half a
brain, I'd just get into city office
myself." And one of my friends said,
"Wow, yeah, you do have half a brain.
Why don't you run?" And the first time
people who knew, they said, "Yeah,
you're either going to get 300 votes or
you're going to get 3,000." And I got
4,000. So that's how I got into
politics. So John was first elected as a
city council member in 2008. He's the
third naturalized citizen from Europe or
the United States to become a Japanese
legislator or in other words the third
white dude to become a politician in
Japan. The other two being Meritute
Turin and Anthony Biani. There have been
a lot of naturalized politicians
including Renho, Yogi, Arafia and
Shinkung. So, if you were to naturalize
and become Japanese, how would you go
about getting elected? Yeah, if you're
going to be a foreigner and you're going
to run for office, then you really have
to be able to read a significant amount
of kanji. Uh, with Google Translate,
it's gotten a lot easier. So, uh, when I
first got elected, there was no Google
Translate, so I was trying to read on
the fly, and my Japanese sucked. You
know, still pretty bad, don't get me
wrong.
Um, but it was really bad and so the end
result was that I struggled a lot. But
that won't happen as much these days.
But still, you got to know your
Japanese.
So, while you don't technically need to
know Japanese, it obviously makes sense
that you be able to communicate in the
language if you want to be successful.
But what you absolutely do need is to be
at least 25 years old, live in the area
you want to represent, and fill out the
official forms from city hall. You also
need to deposit 300,000 yen, which is
refunded if you receive at least 10% of
the votes that the last place candidate
got. In Sukuba, that amounted to about
1,800 votes. So, you'd need at least 180
votes to get your deposit back. But as
John mentioned earlier, during his first
campaign, he got an incredible 4,000
votes, which made me wonder, how did
someone with no political experience,
our lineage, even win? So, what I had to
do is look like Bill Clinton. And that
seemed to work pretty well. People are
attracted to novelty, and I am a
novelty, a unicorn. I would say that a
lot of my voters are young, so they have
been taught from elementary school.
internationalism and to them it doesn't
mean anything. What what does this mean?
They're kids and then suddenly they turn
18 and they can vote and it's like, oh,
maybe that's what it means. And it's
like, yeah, we'll vote for that guy.
Wouldn't that be funny if you won, you
know, the first time? And the times
after that, yeah, they kind of like
having me around. I'm I'm their pet, I
guess you could say. You know, if you've
been in Japan during an election period,
you've probably heard these loud
election trucks usually parked in front
of stations. You may have also noticed
various posters of people in suits or
samurai outfits throughout the city.
These candidates, according to Japanese
law, cannot advertise on TV or radio.
So, public events, speaking on top of
trucks, and plastering their faces all
over the city is pretty much all they're
legally allowed to do. if you happen to
already be wellknown or stand out like
John does, it's a big plus. Like a lot
of these politicians will have like, you
know, two, three, 400 supporters and
they get together and they have the
dauma, you know, the daruma, the the the
face where they paint in the eye or
whatever, you know, and everyone's like
cheering and um I don't have any of
that. This is this is my my office. This
is my group. My my support group is in
the office over
there, right? But it doesn't seem to
matter. So, I don't spend any money on
my elections anymore. The very first
time I spent about 400,000, so $3,500
US. The second election I spent about uh
$1,500 US. My third election I spent $50
US and fourth election 50 as well. And
then to go to the Ibaraki level, I spent
about
$5,000. So, it's it's not a money thing.
John lives in Ibadaki Prefecture where
it's possible that you could be in Tokyo
within an hour if you catch the Tuka
Express. Tukaba City where he lives is
home to a lot of science and research
institutions including Jaxa, Japan's
aerospace exploration agency. So Jon
served his first term as a Tukaba city
assemblyman in 2008. After a few terms
at the city level, he campaigned for an
Ibaraki Prefecture Council seat in 2014,
which he lost. And after taking a break
in 2016, he once again served city as an
assemblyman until 2022 when he ran again
for prefectural council and won. But
something to note is that Jon runs as an
independent which is kind of rare in
Japan. He won without any party support
which according to him wasn't a big
deal. But I still think it has an
influence in the political world. I'm
independent. Okay. So uh I could have
joined a party but I don't see any
reason to. What would they do for me?
They're not going to give me money, help
me get elected. No, they that's not the
way things work. I did see sort of a
point in the last election in that the
parties will do will publish newspapers
and articles and I did not appear
anywhere. Cometo put out a publication
and they literally said, "And don't
bother voting for John cuz he doesn't
stand a chance." which I found I found
disturbing. You know, in any case, uh
that would be the only reason to join a
party is that they would provide a
little bit of political oomph in the in
this in the media sphere,
but you pay for it and that you are
required to vote a certain way, for
example. But despite being a maverick of
sorts, Jon doesn't exactly rock the
boat. Sure, he stands out, but his
policies aren't particularly
controversial in Japan. Uh, I haven't
really screwed anything up too badly.
Uh, very pro- environmental. The kids
really like that. I am relatively
fiscally conservative, so the old people
like that. While filming John for the
day, we stopped by city hall where he
introduced us to his longtime friend and
colleague, Kokosan.
This is my good friend, Mr. Cocoo. He
and I are good drinking buddies.
So this
[Laughter]
One thing I wanted to know was how
John's life changed once he became a
politician. Did people treat him
differently? I mean people treated
already treated me quite differently
when I became a bar owner like then I
was like a shachel kind of you know when
I got elected like then people like oh
wow now he's a politician you know and
it opened up a lot of doors and I really
appreciate that. But when I became the
ken level, the prefecture level, oh my
god, the level of obseess.
Normally I translate Japanese to
English, but for this pricey word,
obsequiousness, I'll do the English to
English translation. Obsequousness means
being excessively eager to please or
obey. I'm still the same dumbass. More
experience, but you know, I don't see
myself as anybody special. You know, I'm
just a guy. Now, it's time to
shamelessly promote the traditional
Japanese handdyed towels that we made,
which are sitting in these boxes right
here. These towels were designed by a
real artist, which was sent over to an
artisan to carve out the pattern, which
was then sent to the dying factory to be
dyed on both sides with high quality
cotton. You can tell it's different from
lower quality stuff when you touch it.
But not only that, when you flip it
around, you can see it's equally as
vibrant due to the double dying process.
You could pin it to the wall like I
have, or you can use these 100% Japanese
cypress hangers, or you can be like me
and actually use it as a hand towel. Our
first design included scenes from
LifeRun from videos over the years.
Look, there's Ako drinking, and there's
Aiko eating natto. And our second
design, this is popular Japanese foods.
Ako's on standby, ready to ship your
order. Go to
shop.lifefrom.com to get yours today.
Yay. Yay.
Okay, back to the video. Now that we
know John's story, what is his role in
the Ibodaki prefectural government? I
represent the people at the
administration to the administration.
And so the administration is the the
governor and his uh civil service. So
there are two main powers in the
prefectural government. The assembly or
geekai which is made up of 62
prefectural counselors like John and the
executive branch are guil Kikan
comprised of various departments are
bureaus and civil servants all led by
the governor. So we can make laws but
generally we are in in oversight looking
at what laws have been proposed by the
governor and his minions and we say yes
yay or nay up down generally they don't
want to bring a law in which is not
going to pass. That's embarrassing that
makes the news. So they will talk to us
first. So this is an important step in
the law making process. But before these
bills are presented to the assemblymen,
where do the ideas even come from? John
explained how bills grow from the ground
up. So, for example, uh daycare is a is
a big one. There is like a group within
the administration that deals with
daycare and so they will listen to the
opinions and then they will formulate a
plan how to deal with a given situation
and this will bubble up through the
administration. Uh you have to have the
funding for it. the group which looks
after a daycare, they only have a set
amount of money. If they're going to
support this particular idea versus that
particular idea, they have to get the
money from somewhere. So even though
they have the idea, they have the need,
you know, the people have told them,
right? They still have to find the money
somewhere. And it often means by
shutting something else down or taking a
slice from here, there, and everywhere.
Anyway, they'll write the law and it
will come to us and we will vote yes or
no, right? So, we can do the same thing
as counselors. We can propose uh propose
something, but the administration's
going to do it. The the civil service is
going to do it. They're the ones who are
going to implement it. And so, yeah,
they'll say, "Yeah, yeah, yeah, okay. We
accept that this new regulation is on
the books. And what's the timeline?" Oh,
well, you know, that's a really, you
know, we want it in the in the paper. it
has to be done by de uh December 31st
such and such a year. So let's say 2
years from now because everything works
so slow, right? Uh and they come back
and oh yeah, no, we couldn't do it in
that time and so they foot drag or they
don't foot drag. They are the ones who
are going to do it. John's been trying
to get two ideas off the ground. One is
to make convenience stores in Ibadaki
hide their cigarettes, which are
normally seen behind the register, and
the other is to build a bus bay at a
busy four-lane road in Sukuba City. John
drove me to the bus bay in question to
show me what the problem is and how he
proposes to help fix it. Here comes two
buses
even. So, they're going to
stop. They're going to stop over
there. Oh, no. It's a private bus.
So now he's
stopping. I don't know what this guy see
already. The bus, you see the bus is
getting into the other lane. Everybody's
going to try and get into the other lane
now, right? But there's too much
traffic and so all of these cars are
cursing that they didn't think that they
needed to get into the other lane.
But uh you know you can see over here
like people who are watching ahead they
are already moving if they
can there are there are three different
kinds of ownership that is to say the
the country the prefecture and the city
own roads. The prefecture owns all of
these four lanes. They are going to have
to discuss the finances. So in fact when
I asked about this in my last question
period there had never been a protocol
for bus bays being installed after a
road was built. So this is something
that the as far as Iaki is concerned
they built the roads 40 years ago and
they had no clue that this was going to
be a problem 40 years later. So the
initial stand of the prefixure is oh
yeah we'd gladly have the city pay for
everything. Right. And of course, the
city is going to be like, "Well, hang on
here. You're the guys who are in charge
of the four-lane roads. So, why should
we pay? You should pay." And somewhere
in the middle will be the compromise.
So, in order to propose these ideas to
his colleagues, John first writes out
the bill in English. His wife will then
translate it into Japanese. And from
there, he'll start approaching other
council members and get a general sense
of will this or won't this pass? like
with his friend Kokabosa who we met
earlier.
And while we were at city hall, John
showed us the assembly hall where the
mayor will propose a bill to the
assemblymen and any citizens who want to
attend.
This is where I used to cause trouble.
So my seat was uh second row of on the
far left. So we have sessions every 3
months. So while you may think
politicians spend all their time in city
halls like this arguing against each
other, it's at the max 3 weeks out of
every 3 months that they'd be here. The
footage from his home is a lot more
representative of what he ends up doing.
He also has to get out and attend
meetings and events like the 13 times he
traveled up to Mito City, the capital of
Ibaraki in the month we filmed him.
I am invited to a lot of different
ribbon cutings or road building budget
meetings for example and I don't know
that I contribute anything but I'm there
like I'm providing oversight is what
really what's going on is that they're
making sure that I know what's going on.
After a day of shooting, John himself
prepared a scrumptious roast chicken as
if it were Christmas.
And as a priceless appetizer, he showed
us some direct to DVD film covers that
he was credited in. Thanks for watching.
See you next time. Peace. And I'm not
going to say it. I'm not going to say
what's life like as a politician where
you're from.
Can you say your catchphrase?
[Music]